To be a historic action to protect Asian-Americans in this country and made that dramatic rise in attacks.
President Biden‛s signing into law and anti-Asian hate crimes bill.
It was overwhelmingly approved by Congress.
And tonight here, that horrific case in New York city, a woman assaulted in broad daylight.
You‛ll remember us reporting here, bystanders appearing to watch it unfold, but doing nothing about it tonight, ABCs, Juju Chang with the survivor of that attack.
Tonight, the woman who survived this brutal attack on a New York city street.
Now speaking out about the trauma, she endured that day, physically I‛m healing well, but mentally, emotionally, I‛m not there yet.
Surveillance video showing 66 year old Vilma carry a Filipino American on our way to church.
When a man suddenly kicks her, knocking her down stomping on her face repeatedly.
Film, his daughter says the attacker hurled racist slurs at her mom F you Asian, you don‛t belong here.
The suspect a homeless man, reportedly with a history of mental illness arrested on hate crime charges.
He pleaded not guilty.
What does justice at the end of the day look like for you？ It‛s time to change the law so that those victims of hate crime should have a voice and should have, um, justice.
In court today, president Biden‛s signing the COVID-19 hate crimes act every time we‛re silent.
Every time we let hate flourish, you make a lot.
Who we are as a nation.
It‛s that silence that Vilma and her daughter are determined to break sharing AAPI stories, flipping the attackers, alleged words to say, AAP, we do belong here and take that power away from that person that decided to inflict this horrible act on my mom.
So brave of Velma to share her story with you, Juju your reporting has been so powerful on all of this for many months.
Now, you and I were on the air for the attacks in Atlanta.
We know that eight died, six were of Asian descent, but this new bill put into law today will actually help.
So many of the other cases we hope.
That have not received the kind of attention that they deserve.
Absolutely.
As you know, a district attorney in Georgia announced hate crime charges against that alleged shooter in Atlanta, but hate crime charges like Vilmos are rare and today‛s new law is designed to make that process easier.
And David, while Vilma is interested in pursuing justice to the enth degree, she also prayed for her attacker and is literally fighting hate with love extraordinary.
And again, brave of Vilma to talk with you.
We‛re going to have much more of Juju‛s interview later tonight, right here on Nightline.
And we‛ll be watching thanks to you.
Hi, when George Stephanopoulos here, thanks for checking out the ABC news YouTube channel.
If you‛d like to get more videos, show highlights and watch live event coverage, click on the right over here to subscribe to our channel.
And don‛t forget to download the ABC news app for breaking news alerts.
Thanks for watching.