Ella roofs has sparked international outrage by forcing a Ryan airplane to divert to Minsk before arresting an opposition journalist on board, Bella roofs grounded the Ryan air passenger plane, flying over its airspace on Sunday.
For what turned out to be false claims of a bomb on board.
The flight was on its way to Lithuania from Greece.
Belorussian authorities ordered a military fighter jet to escort it to the capital city of Minsk.
According to local media, Bella roofs, president Alexander, Luca Shanko had personally deployed the war plain.
No explosives were found on board the jet.
Instead when it reached the ground, authorities detained one of the passengers, Bella journalist, Roman proto Savage.
26 year old proto Savage worked for online new service next up last year, when it broadcast mass protests against Luka Shanko, he‛s now wanted on extremism charges and is accused of inciting riots allegations.
He denies.
A passenger onboard.
The aircraft said proto Savage had his head in his hands and was shaking.
When he realized the flight was diverted to Minsk later, as he was led away, he reportedly remarked I‛ll get the death penalty.
And then when it was announced that, uh, are we going to lengthen Minsk？ so the Romans stand up for Willie, opened the door, take the luggage, and then was trying to split there.
Things like computer gave it to a girlfriend, iPhone or whatever.
It‛s called his phone after seven hours and minutes, the flight retook its course and landed in Vilnius Lithuania with Dwayne as president get Tanis.
Now Saida said Bellaruse must face consequences.
It should be noted that such attacks on the opposition have recently become systematic.
I‛m attending the European council tomorrow, and we will no doubt raise this issue as well.
It‛s time to stop communicating with the regime just by making declarations concrete measures are needed, capable of changing the behavior of the Belarusian regime.
Global leaders followed suit in their condemnation, including us secretary of state Antony Blinken and head of EDU‛s European commission or Cilla Vondra line who tweeted quote those responsible for the Ryanair.
Hijacking must be sanctioned.
Human rights groups say about 35,000 people have been detained in Belarus since August and more than 1000 criminal cases have been launched.