Developing this morning, a new wall street journal report says bill Gates, 2020 resignation from Microsoft's board of directors, coincided with the board investigating a romantic relationship that he had with a Microsoft employee.
CNN, Christine Romans is joining us.
This is a, you know, quite a bombshell what's happening here.
It is,good morning, Brianna, you know, earlier this month, bill and Melinda Gates announced they would be divorcing.
That was news that rocked the world of philanthropy.
Bill Gates in the headlines again this morning.
Microsoft founder, bill Gates, facing misconduct accusations for relationship he had with a Microsoft engineer starting in 2000.
That's according to the wall street journal, the paper found that his March, 2020 resignation from the tech company's board of directors followed an investigation into the affair.
By an outside law firm hired by the board.
The Microsoft board became aware of the affair in 2019 after the employee sent a letter detailing the relationship, the journal reports during the probes of board members thought it was no longer fitting for Gates to continue his role with the company.
The journal said citing people familiar with the matter a spokesperson from Microsoft telling CNN a committee.
Of the board reviewed the concern aided by an outside law firm to conduct a thorough investigation throughout the investigation.
Microsoft provided extensive support to the employee who raised the concern, a spokesperson for Gates admitted to the relationship telling the journal quote, there was an affair almost 20 years ago, which ended amicably his decision to transition off the board was in no way related to this matter.
Okay, so you have to go some distance.
You can't get it nearby.
At the time.
Gates announced his resignation.
He said it was out of a desire to focus on his philanthropic work.
In another report.
The New York times reported that Gates developed a reputation for questionable conduct in work-related settings.
Adding that on at least a few occasions, Mr gates, pursued women who worked for him at Microsoft.
And at the bill and Melinda Gates foundation, the time citing people with direct knowledge of the overtures Gates spokesperson denied any mistreatment of employees to the times and said it is extremely disappointing that there have been so many untruths published about the cause the circumstances and the timeline of bill Gates, divorce.
These revelations come just weeks after Gates and his wife, Melinda announced they were divorcing after 27 years of marriage.
In the case of Melinda.
It's a truly equal partner.
The couple met in 1987 while she was working at Microsoft.
I was new to Microsoft.
There were, there were a lot of men there.
Um, and you know, you, you're still looking around, you know, you're still figuring it out.
But after about a year of that, you know, sort of to our surprise, certainly my surprise, uh, you know, we, we said, Hey, I love you.
And she said, she loved me.
So these headlines come after the wall street journal reported, Melinda Gates was meeting with divorce lawyers back in 2019 after revelations about her husband's connection with accused sex trafficker, Jeffrey Epstein emerged sources told the journal that Gates is concerned about her husband's relationship with Epstein dated all the way back to 2013, especially because Melinda Gates is a global advocate for women and girls.
CNN has not confirmed this or any allegations decided by the journal and the times Brianna.