Hello, and welcome to news review from BBC learning English⢀ I'm Neil and joining me is Catherine⢀ hello, Catherine⢀ hello？ hello everybody⢀ yes⢀ today's story⢀ the remains of a Chinese rocket have landed in the Indian ocean now for a while⢀ It wasn't certain where exactly this stuff was going to land⢀ If you'd like to test yourself on any of the vocabulary you hear in our program today, there is a quiz on our website@bbclearningenglish⢀com.
Now let's hear some more about that story from this BBC news report, weighing 18 tons and traveling to the 17th⢀  miles per hour, identifying exactly where the long March five B rocket will make landfill proved almost impossible until the last minute and made accusations of negligence, Chinese experts at asserted that the debris would likely land in the ocean.
And ultimately they were proved⢀ right⢀ so the remains of a Chinese rocket have landed in the Indian ocean⢀ now there have been some concern from some people about where exactly this rocket was going to land⢀ they were worried about injuries⢀ china insisted that the risk was very low on as it happens.
Nobody, as far as we know was injured after all⢀ catherine⢀ you've been looking at this story across the world's media⢀ you've picked out three words and expressions, which, uh, people will find useful for understanding the story⢀ what are they？ we have DeBry heats up and gumbo⢀ deBry heats up and gamble.
Let's start them with your first headline⢀ yes, we are starting with the South China morning⢀ post the headline, China, us tensions, moved to space as a rocket debris head sport earth, DeVry broken pieces of something larger⢀ yes, no interesting pronunciation for, for this one⢀ the word is spelled D E B R I S.
Now Neil, you are a British English speaker⢀ are you not？ I am⢀ so how do you pronounce this word？ well, I say, I think I say DeBry⢀ debris debris⢀ okay⢀ you will also hear British English speakers saying daybreak⢀ so you can say Deborah or de Bree, but if you are a speaker of American English, you will say in the earth debris, debris, and notice the stress shifts in British English.
It's on the desk⢀ or day the first part of the word in American English⢀ It's the second part of the word debris, but that ass is always silent⢀ yeah⢀ okay⢀ so a bit of a complicated word here pronounced in several different ways, but the most obvious thing is that we don't pronounce the S at the end⢀ why not？.
Uh, because it was a French word originally as it goes⢀ and in French words, often the S isn't pronounced, but we have our British version of this word, debris or debris⢀ yeah⢀ Interesting⢀ this word is neither too formal or too informal⢀ It's suitable for it⢀ yeah⢀ you can use it anywhere in any situation to describe basically.
Broken pieces or something that are often left, scattered around after an accident or some kind of violent, um, event⢀ so after a storm, when the weather's really bad, there's lots of wind⢀ there's lots of rain⢀ you go outside, you will see a rubbish everywhere⢀ bits of trees, broken brunches kind of bins have gone over lots of rubbish in the street after a storm.
That rubbish is DeBry⢀ yeah⢀ and we can also use it in a slightly humorous way to describe, uh, basically a really messy place⢀ yeah⢀ you can talk about the debris that's left after a party⢀ so it's not always natural disasters that can be created, you know, just mess that's created⢀ and in this rocket case.
So talking about debris, meaning pieces of the broken rocket scattered around⢀ okay, let's get a summary.
If you're interested in stories about space, we have one about a rocket that went into space and came back made by space X⢀ where can our viewers find the story you can read about the, you can watch the recycled rocket story by clicking the link⢀ okay⢀ let's have your next headline, please⢀ yes, we are now in the U S and our headline from CNN is China blamed the U S for hyping fears of uncontrolled rocket re-entry as space race heats up.
Heats up becomes more extreme⢀ yes⢀ two words⢀ now, first word hits⢀ h E a T S the second word up U P⢀ so the verb to heat up is a phrasal verb⢀ now, Katherine, I know what to heat up means⢀ that's what I do with my leftovers⢀ um, I get them out of the fridge and I put them in a little bowl and I put them in the microwave and I heat them up.
Is that the same？ to make food hot⢀ yeah⢀ um, you know, it's not quite the same, but when you heat food up, you make it hot⢀ you take it from a cold state to a hot state⢀ now, if we think about this more metaphorically, we often use the idea of getting hot or heating up to describe a situation which is getting more serious, more pressured.
More anxious, more important, more tense, often more angry⢀ so the, the space race is heating up⢀ It means it's getting more intense⢀ It's getting more serious⢀ there's more pressure⢀ so we could use words like intensify or agitate⢀ yeah⢀ good, good synonyms⢀ good synonyms⢀ so if you think about yourself at work, you know, you've got an important meeting, there's a job to be done.
The deadline's coming more and more people are asking you questions about it⢀ you know that if this job isn't done properly, there's gonna be some problems⢀ so you can say that the situation is he saying, Oh, up, or you can say that the heat is off⢀ yeah, definitely⢀ the heat is on and we use, as you said, heat.
Metaphorically to describe sort of uncomfortable situations⢀ If you can imagine something being too hot, you don't feel good⢀ yes, exactly⢀ too hot to handle⢀ we, we talk about that when there's a situation that is really serious and you don't want to get involved, or if you are involved, there's going to be trouble.
Well, okay⢀ let's get a summary⢀
If you would like to watch another story about a situation where things really heated up, we have the perfect one for you about the Royal family⢀ yes, we do⢀ so just click the link to find out more now time for your next headline, please⢀ catherine⢀ yes, we are in the UK⢀ now with the Telegraph, China wins gamble after space rocket DeBry crushed lands in Indian ocean gamble, a plan that has both a risk of failure and the chance of success.
Yes⢀ g a M B L E⢀ now it's a known in our headline, but it can also be a verb⢀ that's right⢀ yes⢀ and people probably know the verb to gamble connected to betting⢀ so, yeah⢀ casinos horse racing, that kind of thing⢀ yes⢀ where you put some, you place some money on the result of something of race or a game of cards.
And if you guess, or predict the result correctly, you get more money back⢀ If you got it wrong, you lose your money⢀ now the idea of gambling is about risk⢀ Isn't it⢀ you take a risk, you might have a good outcome⢀ you might have a bad outcome, but you essentially⢀ you don't know for sure what's going to happen.
And that's the sense it's being used here⢀ Isn't it⢀ It's not about putting money on something in the hope of winning more money⢀ no it's about here⢀ the referring to the, the idea that it wasn't certain where this rocket debris was going to land and the gamble was, will it land in the ocean or will it land in a populated area and caused some damage？.
Now, China said that this wasn't a big risk, but some other people said, well, actually, That was a big risk here that could have been a lot of damage⢀ and that's why they saying China won the gamble because there was no damage eventually⢀ yeah⢀ we use set expressions with this as well⢀ take a gamble and a bit of a gamble.
Yes, absolutely⢀ and it's where you do something⢀ not really knowing whether the outcome will be good or bad⢀ yeah⢀ now a person who gambles is a gambler⢀ but that doesn't mean that this is a person in a casino or in a bookmakers putting bets on horses⢀ It can describe a type of personality that enjoys risk.
Yes, it can obviously, I mean, if you are a gambler, you can say I'm a gambler⢀ I like going to casinos, but you can also just use it about your attitude to life⢀ you know, if you think, well, I'm going to do this thing at work⢀ If it goes, if it goes badly, there'll be troubled⢀ but if it goes well, everybody will say I'm fantastic.
Then your personality type is you like a gamble？ you're gambling⢀ okay, well, let's get a summary.
Time now for a recap of vocabulary, please, Catherine⢀ yes, we had debris broken pieces of something larger heats up becomes more extreme and gamble, a plan that has both a risk of failure and a chance of success⢀ If you'd like to test yourself on the vocabulary⢀ There's a quiz on our website@bbclearningenglish⢀com and we are all over social media.
Join us next week and stay safe⢀ Goodbye⢀ bye.