Columbia is marking one month since a wave of deadly protests began, they started as an outcry against a controversial tax reform, but soon turned into a national uprising against growing poverty and inequality.
Weeks of negotiations to end the unrest have failed to bear fruit and the prospect of a peaceful solution seemed to slip even further on Friday when president Eva Dukey announced.
He was deploying the military.
After more people died in demonstrations, plumes of smoke tower above the city of Papa.
John like monuments to the resistance.
A month of protest has turned streets across the country to smell, drink battles garbage from what they see as their fight for justice.
because the message we want to deliver is that we‛re tired of so much injustice from this corrupt government of so much inequality.
We‛re not asking for any handouts and we‛re not asking them to give us anything.
We‛re only asking for an opportunity to grow for quality, not only for the rich, but also for the poor.
The protests erupted when president  sought to raise taxes, to pay for the pandemic, the blow back forced him to kill the bill, but the outcry continued and outrage over the government‛s handling of a crisis that seen unemployment, double and inequality.
Surge attempts to broken into the standoff have so far proved few towels.
According to official figures, more than 45 people have been killed dozens, more disappeared, and thousands on both sides were injured, but human rights groups say the real toe is likely much higher and it‛s only likely to get worse in the days ahead.
On Friday, president dookay said he‛s deploying the army to the epicenter of the unrest colleagues where at least three people were killed in the last 24 hours.
actually be absolutely clear.
Yeah.
As of tonight we begin the maximum deployment of military assistance in the city of galleys and the department of it by islands of anarchy, do not have a place  no, boy.
Next is still in restaurant pace.
Meeting with Columbia‛s vice president on Friday, us secretary of state Anthony Blinken expressed his concern over the deepening crisis in the country, backing the people‛s right to protest peacefully for now, though, the deathly cat and mouse game on the streets of Columbia continues.