Four days after torrential rains triggered deadly floods in Western Germany survivors have now turned their focus toward the daunting task of rebuilding.
But with emergency services, still busy looking for bodies and securing vital infrastructure.
Many residents are left to seek help from volunteers or go with alone son sausages and beer.
It looks like a village.
But it's not what it seems.
This is just a break time for the volunteers organizing an arduous relief effort.
Now that the flood water has subsided solidarity is the one thing on everyone's minds here right now, and getting people who have been affected by the floods back on their feet, as quickly as possible.
People have traveled from nearby villages and further to get here to lend a helping hand with the kids.
Over the weekend around 200 cologne football fans descended on the region and have been distributed around the effected areas.
They've been helping locals by rolling up their sleeves, to clear debris from homes, restaurants, and the ruined beer, whole cologne fan Marco helped organize the effort you can't leave people on their own.
You just have to help.
If it had happened to me, then I'd want someone to.
So I think it's great that people are lending a hand.
The generous response has stunned locals, including this hairdresser.
She's had a business here for 12 years, but I think there were so many people out there that you don't even know.
I don't even know where they come from.
They're out here helping to clear up so much willingness to help.
It's wonderful com that's short, short.
Despite all the volunteers, many people have been left.
Wondering why there hasn't been more help from the authorities.
Yeah, those at the top are trying to bring order to the chaos, but it's not really working.
A lot of help is coming from volunteers and residents.
They're showing an awful lot of initiative, but you can't really say that people at the top of helping, um, yeah.
It's, it's a spirit.
It's Suzanne, that's just fun.
With so many areas overwhelmed by the floods rescue services, say they're at breaking point.
it's pretty difficult to get help to everyone and we have to prioritize.
If we get a report that someone's still trapped in a building, then people with watering their basements, they end up being pushed to the back of the queue.
There's much work to be done, but many volunteers say they'll stick around long after this week.
We'll go chef, our boss has given us Monday and Tuesday off so we can use the time to finish the job, support the local with many residents, still wondering how this disaster could have happened.
That help will be much appreciated.
Let's bring in our correspondent.
Julia saw deli.
Now she's an RV dealer.
That's one of the town's worst hit by the floods.
Uh, tell us, it's been five days since the flood waters, inundated Arvada and the surrounding region.
How are things looking on the ground there now？ any news of the dozens of people reported missing？ well, the devastation is just astounding.
The streets are filled with debris here, here.
For example, we have this massive pile of books.
This used to be an antiquity store, and now everything is completely destroyed.
The ground floors of homes have been.
Completely filled with water and mud.
So residents have been trying to clean everything up.
They have put all their furniture on the streets.
And the problem here is that the streets are quite small.
So it is difficult.
For example, for big trucks or excavators to come in and take all these things out and bring them to the dump.
So it is going to take a few days for the town to be cleaned up, but it's not.
The loss of objects of things that is also the loss of lives, the number of the dead, it keeps rising up to 116 people dead and only this region.
And, uh, the authorities, uh, expect, uh, more casualties to, to emerge.
Now, chancellor, I'm going to, uh, came to the region there on Sunday.
She, uh, she visited and talked to residents.
Tell us a bit more about what she said on that.
Yeah, well, the chancellor took stock of the devastation that occurred in this region.
She said the German language doesn't have any words that are able to describe the, the devastation.
Uh, she also said that she is very much aware that it is going to take a long time for the towns to be cleaned up and rebuilt.
And, uh, she promised the, the population that the government is going to be there in the longterm to try to support them.
She thanked, uh, the rescue crews and the many volunteers who came and showed solidarity with the local residents and are helping, uh, with the cleanup.
Do you want me to thank you so much.
That was Julius on deli there in Alma.
Well, many people are wondering how this could have happened, uh, that people in the region who were so badly effected were not warned.
Well, let's talk now to Keisler too, about that.
He's from the German research center for geosciences in Potsdam.
He specializes in flood risk.
Forecasting Dr.
Shorter.
Thanks for being with us.
Europe has a sophisticated flood warning system in place.
You know, all about that yet these floods seem to have taken people completely by surprise what happened？ good morning.
Uh, first of all, yeah, the, the flood warning actually is a very difficult, uh, undertaking because, um, it is based on information that is about the future and forecasts about the future.
Always difficult to.
Uh, particularly in the case of, uh, flash flood events, as we have seen in, uh, in our Wila and other regions last week, because these flood events have a really rapid onset and you don't have much time actually to provide your information before the flood already occurs to the people.
Uh, you have technical issues to solve, to, uh, give them.
Uh, forecast about the location, where it is going to happen.
You have to give the information to the people on the ground.
You have to reach these people.
And this is, uh, always talked about that is the last critical mile.
So you have to reach the people, you have to disseminate your information, and you often don't have a confirmation that the information has been received and the general information.
And that's that's useful.
And I wanted to ask you specifically about what happened in this case, because a British researcher, uh, Hannah cloak, you might know her, she worked on Europe's flood warning system.
She alleges that the system in this case did work.
She says that German authorities, however, uh, even though they were given precise warnings failed to act, what can you tell us about.
But I don't have actually the, the, uh, the company information from the situation on the ground.
Uh, I know that the ethos system did work very well also that the German weather service had, uh, provided information that something is going to happened beforehand.
But there's, I would just want, wanted to say it, it's difficult to convey this information to the people and also to convey information to the people.
They need to do in these cases.
Often people have some experience with flooding, but this has not been the same type of flooding, uh, or the same severity of flooding as it happened right now.
So maybe they might have underestimated what is going to happen.
And this is something that is very, very difficult to control and very, very difficult to, uh, to provide the information the people actually need to do in such cases.
Do you have any advice on how catastrophes like this could be.
I think, first of all, we really need to take every flood event like this, to really learn from that, not only in this region, but also in other regions.
So I think everyone now has to ask himself the question, okay, what would happen in my place？ if such a rainfall would have fallen in such a short time amount.
And with this information, you can then try to find out ways.
Uh, the impacts of flooding in your region, you can then decide what could be, uh, measures to counteract.
And there you have different possibilities.
You can try to control the hazard, but in cases of the event that you see last week, this is something that is purely beyond control of, of technical measures.
So you also need to think about how can I reduce my exposure to flooding？ how can I reduce my vulnerability to flooding？ so what can I do to avoid it？ uh, impacts of flooding if technical control measures do not work anymore.
Gotcha.
Just wanted to thank you very much for talking with us.
That was  from the German research center for geosciences in Pottstown.
Thank you very much.