That's Israel firing missiles into Northern Gaza as Hamas fires over 45 rockets aimed towards Jerusalem.
This is according to new reporting out from the IDF.
That's the Israeli defense force.
It comes as tensions.
Continue to ratch up in the region.
Following what has been a week's long new spate of military conflict Trey Gates joins us now from Israel with details on the ground.
Hi Trey.
Jillian good afternoon.
This was a red line for Israel firing on Jerusalem.
Earlier this evening, seven rockets targeted the city and dozens of rockets have targeted communities along the Gaza border here where we are standing.
The past 30 minutes have been quiet.
But the IDF, the Israeli defense forces are preparing.
They say four days of fighting along the Gaza border.
If we spoke earlier with sources inside Gaza who have confirmed that the Israelis are now responding with airstrikes inside the Gaza strip.
According to the Palestinian health ministry, nine Gazans have been killed, including.
Three children in this Israeli, retaliation.
How did we get here?
That's the big question?
Well, this week has been extremely tense.
There were protests across Jerusalem that turned to riots early this morning, more than 300 Palestinians were injured at the Al-Aqsa mosque as Israeli security forces stormed in all of this related to two major issues.
Having to do with access to a Locksa and also the shake Jarrod neighborhood in Jerusalem.
Those are very local and focused issues for this conflict.
But as we have seen tonight, this is evolving into a much larger situation.
I want to get just some information that we're getting here from the Israeli military, they are calling this a severe assault on Israel.
They say they hold Hamas.
The group in control of Gaza, responsible saying Hamas will bear the consequences.
We also know according to the Israeli defense spokesperson that.
A Hamas military commander was targeted in some of this Israeli retaliation this hour.
And this takes things to a different level inside Gaza because the factions there then say they need to respond.
There are two big factions inside Gaza.
One is Hamas and the other is Islamic jihad.
Both of them have fired rockets tonight into Southern Israel and central Israel in the past, the last major round.
Only focused on Islamic jihad.
So the fact that Hamas is getting involved in the fight means that this is turning into a serious conflict for the region.
And as you can see behind me, police have blocked off roads leading to the Gaza border itself.
We're just about a mile away from the border and there are bomb shelters opened all around us.
It's very quiet in this city of stood up because people are preparing for further conflict.
Trey.
Thanks for being there for us.
Stay safe.
We'll check back in with you later.
Appreciate it.