When it was happening to me, I thought that I was the only one, not only with him, but in the world who is surviving, something like this.
Serbian actor Milena Redulovic shared her story of rape in January.
It was like a dumb  broke setting off a metoo wave empowering women across the region to speak up about a taboo subject.
Well, this story is shaped Serbia from the gound.
Milena has accused famous produce and drama teacher Miroslav Alexi of raping her when she was 17 and studying at the prestigious acting school in Belgrade, several other women from the same school have come forward with similar accusations.
Alexa has since been charged with rape and other illegal sexual acts.
He denies wrongdoing and is being held in detention, the publicity around the case, unleash the tide of testimonies and brought another case back into the spotlight.
I remember clearly, um, hearing about Milena's story and being in tears of joy, I was just thinking of that.
My mission to encourage other people to speak has started.
Daniella Steinfeld is a Serbian filmmaker now based in New York.
Last year, she released a documentary examining the aftermath of sexual assault.
Including her own recently, she revealed the name of the man.
She says raped her well-known Serbian actor Branislav Lečić who denies the allegation.
Others have come out with similar accusations and investigation is underway and no charges have yet been made violence against women is a serious concern in Serbia.
The country ratified this symbol convention to protect women, but reporting and conviction rates are extremely low.
Most of the victims in the Balkan region are still in silence.
The self silencing is a self protection because one thing is to survive sexual assault and reach for safety.
The other thing is to survive the unpredictability of a backlash disbelief, shaming.
Daniela left Serbia, abandoning her successful acting career there from a PTSD and from pretty much dysfunctional person that I was for years, I raise up to make the film to make something that it was helpful for many people.
And that is something that has healed me.
For Milena, one reason to share her story was to make people see what's been hiding in plain sight.
i knew that it is going to be interesting for everybody because I was this protected princess girl from a good family and everybody would have like, Oh, she's leading such a fairytale.
So I knew that it's going to be like, Oh my God, like her, if I kept talked to Daniella, um, right after the assaults, um, I would tell her.
Uh, to not be afraid, go tell your parents now.
Yeah, and I would tell her that it's not only your case.
And to know that no matter how difficult and long, long, long time it's needed, the healing is possible.