It's low tide at Cambodia's Tom lane, SAP Southeast Asia is the largest freshwater lake fishing boats returned to the docks.
Well, children play on the mud flats.
They're joyful cries are a stark contrast to Tom's the room's childhood.
Yeah, I believe of watching.
I'm like Dalton in my childhood.
I helped my mother make steamed rice cakes to sell.
It says the 41 year old crouching as she ski was small fish.
For as long as the room can remember, work has been a part of her life.
I needed to wake up very early in the morning.
I wrote a boat from one village to the next to sell the cakes.
Yeah.
After her father passed away.
So the room had to support her mother.
The one that was why I quit school.
So room story is not uncommon.
19% of Cambodian children aged five to 17 work most in agriculture, especially fisheries fishing and rice cultivation are the backbone of the country's economy.
They're integral to Cambodian cultural identity and food security.
While Tom lay stopped, lake contributes over half of the country's fish production.
It's 4.8 million residents are some of Asia's poorest.
Many faced extreme poverty and parents have no choice, but to send their children to work explains one time from the commune committee for women and girls.
pause 10 to 15 years.
There's been a lot of child labor in the community.
They always bring their children fishing with them and they use the children to work for others to get extra income for their family.
Well, while it's legal in Cambodia for children aged 15 to 17.
What's not legal is when that work violates their rights.
Child.
Labor is defined as a work, but is inappropriate for chance age, if it affects or interferes with a child's education, or if it is likely to harm their health and safety that's child labor expert, Arianne John, Tom from the food and agriculture organization of the United nations.
She says that when children, without on an education, they miss out on so much more child labor hinders children from reaching their full potential and their future chance of getting decent employment, child labor, pet Patriots, a cycle of rural poverty.
Quite FAO is working closely with the Cambodian government and partner organizations to address the root causes of child labor.
This includes developing awareness, raising materials and visual tools to promote gender equity and to protect children from hazardous work in fisheries.
FAO also provides trainings to fisheries association.
In helping identify and prevent child labor.
Some children took part in a training on child labor prevention as chief of the community fisheries committee.
He travels to fishing villages in Kampong tenon province to raise awareness about child labor.
Today, he's organized a community meeting in Khan Lang pay village  I visited some families and explained to each family about child labor to make it clear to them.
fishing villages are often isolated with limited access to schools and transportation.
As a result, many adults Fisher folk are illiterate and face poverty.
Children's mission is to encourage them to send their children to school.
He explains to them how the communities stands to benefit as well.
suppose we can eliminate child labor in the community.
In that case, our community gets many advantages.
Why once enough children going back to school, then there are resources in the company.
Yeah, early morning in condominium, paid village, only fish of folk and a chorus of cicadas are awake at this hour.
So room's door touch.
I'm concierge sits cross-legged in the dark, concentrated by her book, which she reads under Torchlight.
Normally the teenager would be getting up at this hour to go fishing with her.
But these days, she wakes up early to study every day I get up at five.
O'clock read a little and get ready to go to school at six o'clock.
No mom boy, thanks to joint efforts by FAO and the Cambodian government come see is enrolled in school.
Instead of child labor, every day, she rides a motorbike to school, denied it on the mound.
No, my own puck.
It takes.
At 7:00 AM I arrive at school, but then I leave school at 10 o'clock.
I arrive home at 11 o'clock.
I have lunch.
And then I go fishing with my dad.
she helps her dad catch real fish, used to make Prague a salty fermented fish paste, commonly used in Cambodian cuisine long long.
When I go fishing, I throw gillnets.
I released the fish from the gillnets and I take off the scales or the efficient skin.
Then she helps her mother clean and prepare the fish to either smoke or sell I'm back home at five in the evening, I helped my mother peel the remaining fish until it's done at around six or six.
these days just catching enough fish for dinner can be a challenge as fish numbers in toddler lace-up lake, continue to decline even more reason for children like come yet to get an education.
And man, that Dean, if my daughter could pass her grade 12, I would be very excited.
She wants her daughter to have the opportunities that she never had.
I've owned  I do not want my children to be illiterate.
Like me fighting child labor through education helps break the cycle of poverty.
It keeps children safe and teaches them new skills to find jobs that earn a more stable income
concierge performs well at school.
And although she still works for her family.
She attends class regularly.
Thanks to the full support of her.
Her dream is to one day become a teacher in her own community.
A nickname could come from, I want to be a teacher in the village because there is always a shortage of teachers.
If there is a teacher in a village, it is easy to educate children and allow them to acquire knowledge, which just goes to show that fighting child labor through education.
Really does benefit everyone.