Bolivia and Peru are countries in South America.
The weather is usually warm there.
It does not snow.
Snow falls only in the mountains.
It snows there last week.
Temperatures are below zero.
It is perfect weather for snowfall.
Snow covers parts of Bolivia and Peru.
People do not expect it.
People see snow for the first time.
They are happy.
They throw snowballs at each other in the streets.
Drivers are not so happy.
Many cars get stuck in the snow.
They cannot move.
Local authorities in a Bolivian town must cancel a football match.
Weather forecasts say that cold weather will continue until the end of the week.
Difficult words: temperature (how cold or warm something is), snowfall (the time when snow falls down from the sky), expect (to think that something will happen), forecast (when someone says what the situation will be in the future).