Dozens of demonstrators spilling into the streets of Cuba.
This weekend calling for an end of the 62 year communist regime, chance of we want freedom echoing through the streets, protestors, dumping trash and throwing rocks.
Demonstrations sparked by chronic food shortages and blackouts in Miami protest in solidarity with her.
We've been waiting for change for so long.
Maria Figaro has family in Cuba.
I don't even know what their situation is right now.
An economic crisis exacerbated by the pen.
And no access to approved COVID vaccines, a perfect storm for anti regime, anger that spread rapidly as more Cubans recently gained access to the internet.
You can present Diaz canal today, blaming the unrest on US the lack of medicine and food.
All those topics that are embedded in our society as dissatisfaction.
What is the origin？ it's a blockade.
They simply are not hearing the voices.
Uh, of the Cuban people, uh, people deeply, deeply, deeply.
Uh, the repression president Obama established diplomatic relations with Cuba and removed it from the US list of state sponsors of terrorism.
But the Trump administration put Cuba back on that list, imposing tougher sanctions, which president Biden has not lifted.
They call them the government government cubit or refrain from violence or attempts to silence the voice of the people.
So far Biden's been much tougher on Cuba than president Obama was a senior officials saying when people protest for human rights, the administration will stand with them.
Thanks for watching our YouTube channel follow today's top stories and breaking news by downloading the NBC news app.