The conflict in Northern Ethiopia has displaced hundreds of thousands of people and rattled.
The region observers, fear instability in the largest country in the horn of Africa could spread beyond its borders.
Here's how it got to this point on November 4th, 2020 forces loyal to the Tigray people's liberation front, or TPLF attacked federal military bases in Northern Ethiopia.
According to the federal government prime minister, Abbey Ahmed said the attack crossed a red line and ordered the military to confront TPLF forces.
This, he said came after me.
Of provocation and incitement number six, the Ethiopian military said it launched a campaign to retake TPLF strongholds in the north using precision airstrikes and ground forces to attack military targets, including to Grisel the largest city McCullough.
However officials say there have been civilian casualties, including non-military.
Such as schools, places of worship and infrastructure, to understand the roots of the conflict, you have to go back decades.
Great.
Ethiopia is Northern most region played a vital role in the country's recent history.
TPLF was an armed political movement that helped liberate Ethiopia from the brutal Dirk regime.
Which finally fell from power in 1991.
Then at the gray, an ex fighter Mellison ally led the new coalition government in 1991 that instituted a system known as ethnic federalism.
Which divided the country along ethnic lines into 10 regions with some autonomy, malice and the coalition of political parties.
He founded the Ethiopian people's revolutionary democratic front or EPR RDF held near total control in the country.
Political dissent and free speech were severely restricted, but the country also enjoyed rapid economic growth during malice.
This time, with impressive advances in the industrial sector, still ethnic resentment also grew to grants comprised only 6% of the population, but held outsized power in the military business and politics Melisse died in 2012.
Widespread protests followed leading to the resignation of his successor prime minister, Holly Merriam desolate.
Then Abby Ahmed, a young ethnic Oromo, rose to power in 28.
Abby instituted a raft of reforms, including negotiating a peace deal with neighboring Eritrea and releasing political prisoners.
In 2019, he was awarded the Nobel peace prize, but some of Abby's reforms also deepened divisions in 2019.
He dissolved the ruling party, the EPA RDF, and created the prosperity.
The TPLF refused to join the newly created party by September, 2020, the feud escalated the Tigray region held elections, defying the central government, which had postponed national elections because of the coronavirus.
The central government called the elections illegal.
The rift grew in October when the central government suspended funding for and cut ties with the TPLF to Grise administration said this amounted to a declaration of war.
And once the war began, it quickly escalated on November 14th, the conflict spread in the region beyond its borders.
When the TPLF launched rocketed.
Against neighboring Eritrea TPLF leaders accused Eritrea of involvement in the conflict and said the country was a legitimate target because as Asmara airport and other locations in Eritrea were being used to support Ethiopian, federal.
On November 28th days after surrounding the city of McCullough, Ethiopian, federal forces retook the city center, its airport and military base on the same day, Abby declared an end to the conflict.
He termed a law enforcement.
But later TPLF leader to Brett Sian, Gabri, Mikael vowed to fight off the ensuing conflict has already involved neighboring states and shaken the horn of Africa, which has long viewed Ethiopia as a pillar of regional stability as is often the case in war.
The most vulnerable people bear the brunt of the.
Cellular service and internet access in the region have largely been cut off communications blackout makes it nearly impossible to get accurate information about the conflict and its humanitarian costs.
Tens of thousands of civilians fled to gray, many on foot or on rickety boats across Ethiopia is to cause a river crowding into refugee camps across the Sudanese border.
Although the fighting slowed in late December its impact continues with tens of thousands internally displaced and seeking refuge elsewhere into gray aid workers were denied access to refugee camps by the federal government relief agencies warned of continued dire conditions in what they called a full-scale humanitarian crisis in the region.
As access to parts of the Tigray region is still restricted.
The UN and other organizations say some people have died of starvation and many more are at risk.
In addition to the spread of COVID-19 refugees in the camps in Sudan say they won't return to their homes because they fear for them.
And the long-term direction of the conflict remains uncertain.