No one knows why 14 Asian elephants left a protected nature area in China and started walking north about a year ago.
But after covering 500 kilometers, the elephants seem to be heading home.
The elephants are protected in China.
There are only about 300 in the country.
During the year that the elephants walked, they became famous in China and around the world.
They ate crops on farms.
They entered buildings to find food.
Government officials used large trucks, groups of workers and drones to watch the elephants’ activities.
The animals made it close to Kunming, a large city in Yunnan province, before turning around.
One adult male separated from the group.
He was captured and taken back to the protected nature reserve.
By the end of the day Sunday, the elephants were still about 200 kilometers from the reserve.
People who have been watching and keeping the elephants safe helped them avoid traffic.
They used food to guide them toward a bridge where they could cross the Yuanjiang river.
A statement sent from the National Forestry and Grassland Administration said now that the elephants have crossed the river, they are in a safer habitat and making progress toward home.
I’m Dan Friedell.